<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologeticall declaration of the conscientious Presbyterians of the province of London, and of many thousands of other faithfull, and Covenant-keeping citizens, and inhabitants within the said city and suburbs thereof. Wherein their firmnesse and faithfulnesse to their first principles, and to their Solemn League and Covenant is conscientiously declared; and the Covenant-breaking and apostacie of others is disclaimed and abhorred before God and the whole world. Januarie, the 24th, 1649.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3539B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E539_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865003</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E539[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologeticall declaration of the conscientious Presbyterians of the province of London, and of many thousands of other faithfull, and Covenant-keeping citizens, and inhabitants within the said city and suburbs thereof. Wherein their firmnesse and faithfulnesse to their first principles, and to their Solemn League and Covenant is conscientiously declared; and the Covenant-breaking and apostacie of others is disclaimed and abhorred before God and the whole world. Januarie, the 24th, 1649.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <p>
                     <name type="place">London,</name>
                     <date>Printed in the yeer, 1649.</date>
                  </p>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  England --  London --  History.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGETICALL DECLARATION Of the Conſcientious <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of the <hi>Province</hi> of LONDON, and of <hi>many thouſands</hi> of other faithfull, and <hi>Covenant-keeping Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> within the ſaid City and Suburbs thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherein their <hi>firmneſſe</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> to their firſt <hi>Principles,</hi> and to their <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly declared; And the <hi>Covenant-breaking</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> of <hi>Others</hi> is diſclaimed and abhorred before GOD and the whole World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Januarie,</hi> the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1649.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezekiel, 17, 15, 18, 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Shall they proſper, ſhall they eſcape, that do ſuch things? or ſhall they break the Covenant, and be delivered?</p>
               <p>Seeing they have deſpiſed the Oath, by breaking the Covenant (when as, lo, they had given their hand) and have done all theſe things.</p>
               <p>Therefore, thus ſaith the Lord God, As I live, ſurely, mine Oath which they have deſpiſed, and my Covenant which they have broken, even it will I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe upon their own heads.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Job, <hi>22, 30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The innocent ſhall deliver the Iland; and it ſhall be preſerved by the pureneſs of thy hands.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeer, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117236:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117236:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, It is prudentially conſidered and concluded on by the <hi>Subſcribers</hi> hereof, that (ſeeing their reverend <hi>Miniſters Repreſentation,</hi> with ſubſcription of their Names hath not taken that happie effect which was deſired, nor ſtayed the hands of thoſe to whom it was directed) therefore the publiſhing of their names that have ſubſcribed to this <hi>Apologeticall-Declaration,</hi> will in like manner, do but little good, in that reſpect; And, therefore, although they are upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to the honour of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> they are not, now, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, in regard of the preſent over-awing Power of the Sword; but may and ſhall in due time appear in publick, with more ample and (we hope) moſt ſatisfactory Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the juſt Reaſons of this their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117236:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE the <hi>Subſcribers</hi> of this our <hi>Apologeticall Declaration,</hi> who deſire to approve our ſelves ſincere <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of the true <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion, Presbyterian Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the honorable, and, lately, famous and renowned <hi>City of London,</hi> who have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially adhered unto the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in its firſt and ſecond War againſt the Kings Forces, for the defence of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> His <hi>Majeſties Perſon, Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> the <hi>Rights and Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> and, in them, the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Kingdom: Calling to minde our ſolemn en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, not onely by our <hi>Proteſtation, May,</hi> 5th, 1641, but eſpecially our <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> which was ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and unanimouſly ſworn unto, <hi>with our hands lifted up to the high and holy God of Heaven, that we would really, ſincerely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, through the grace of God, in our ſeverall Callings, and with our lives and eſtates, endevour the preſervation of them all;</hi> Artic: 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. And, being in our Conſciences perſwaded and aſſured of our indiſpenſible obligation ſo to do, becauſe moſt deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by our ſaid <hi>Covenant, not to ſuffer our ſelves, directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion, or terror, to be divided or withdrawn from that Cauſe which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdom, and honour of the King: But, all the dayes of our lives zealouſly and conſtantly to continue therein againſt all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Art: 6. And, whereas, by wofull experience, we are made very ſenſible of the dangerous <hi>effects</hi> of the <hi>violation</hi> of all our <hi>Covenant-concernments,</hi> and of the diſappointment of our hopes of reaping the expected fruits of this defenſive war, for which, we the <hi>Subſcribers,</hi> have, many of us, adventured our lives, and moſt of us, our eſtates, in a meaſure, beyond our abilities, beſides the Common Taxes that have been impoſed upon us. And, though we cannot but with bleeding and trembling hearts complain that <hi>our Cauſe</hi> doth in theſe ſad and perillous times in which we live, meet with ſuch violent <hi>oppoſition,</hi> ſuch mighty <hi>lets</hi> and <hi>impediments</hi> as we are not able to ſuppreſſe and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117236:3"/>yet, conſidering with our ſelves, that what we cannot ſuppreſſe or overcome we are obliged to reveal and make known. <hi>Artic:</hi> 6. Being alſo moved with fear, leſt in this time of imminent danger to all that is dear unto us, our <hi>ſilence</hi> ſhould be taken for <hi>conſent,</hi> and ſo contract upon our ſelves the guilt of betraying <hi>Religion, King, Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of this Nation; having alſo no other way left us to ſet our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences at liberty from the aforeſaid guilt we might contract by our <hi>ſinfull ſilence,</hi> in this juncture of time. We do, therefore, with all <hi>ſincerity, fidelity, zeal,</hi> and <hi>humility,</hi> before the moſt juſt and righteous Lord of heaven and earth, make known unto all the three Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to all the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed-Churches,</hi> and unto the whole <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> not onely the <hi>diſ-ſatisfaction</hi> of our Spirits, at the <hi>late</hi> and <hi>preſent tranſactions</hi> of thoſe who have forcibly aſſumed the <hi>Supreme-power</hi> into their own hands: But alſo do make this our following moſt ſolemn and ſerious <hi>Apologeticall Declaration</hi> for our <hi>clearing</hi> and <hi>juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from allowing or aſſenting to the <hi>illegall actings</hi> of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times. And that we may alſo publiſh unto the world the grounds of theſe our moſt juſt exceptions and neceſſitated com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints herein, we declare, That, not onely, in <hi>generall,</hi> our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Cauſe</hi> before mentioned is perverted, deſerted, apoſtatized, and fallen-from, by thoſe who moſt injuriouſly and falſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach us with <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> for not aſſociating with them, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them companie in their unwarrantable wayes; But, alſo, in <hi>particular,</hi> that it is perverted, and abuſed in <hi>every part</hi> &amp; <hi>branch</hi> therof. As firſt, in point of our <hi>Religion,</hi> which we are moſt deeply engaged by <hi>Covenant</hi> to preſerve and reform in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>purity;</hi> Whereas in our own experience (confirmed by the <hi>Parliaments</hi> firſt <hi>Remonſtrance, Exact Collect:</hi> pag. 4.) <hi>Religion,</hi> in its <hi>purity</hi> was greatly endangered, in the <hi>Prelates</hi> times in the <hi>Doctrinall-part,</hi> by the errors of <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſme;</hi> and in <hi>worſhip,</hi> with ſuperſtitious <hi>Innovations:</hi> And, in our ſad apprehenſion, the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is, now adayes, not onely more endangered through the increaſe of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> but of moſt blaſphemous <hi>Antiſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uniſme, Antitrinitarianiſme, Antinomia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Socinianiſme,</hi> and many other ſuch like heterodox <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and damnable <hi>doctrines:</hi> But alſo in point of <hi>worſhip,</hi> which,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117236:4"/>inſtead of fear of corrupting, is, now, in great danger of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Nulling,</hi> by accurſed opinions both againſt the very <hi>being</hi> of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> the <hi>ſet-times</hi> and <hi>dayes</hi> appointed by God for their <hi>adminiſtration;</hi> and even of the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> appointed by Jeſus Chriſt, for their <hi>diſpenſation.</hi> Which doth the more ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affect our hearts, and enforce this juſt <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi> becauſe of that ſo eagerly endeavoured unwarrantable <hi>Tolerating</hi> of them all (except, in that ſubtil exception of theirs, of the open practiſe of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacie</hi>) as if it were <hi>That Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience</hi> which we have all this while engaged for; But, rather, againſt which, We do not onely proteſt, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe profeſſe and declare that it was, onely, <hi>a Liberty of Conſcience from ſin and error,</hi> which we propounded in our <hi>freedome</hi> from our former <hi>Egyptian Taskmasters</hi> the <hi>Prelates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, we further declare againſt the perverting of <hi>our Cauſe,</hi> in relation to the preſervation of the <hi>rights</hi> and <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament.</hi> For, although we were not able to preſerve and defend them, when violated by that <hi>unpattern'd and horrid force</hi> upon the <hi>Houſe, Decemb:</hi> 6, and 7, laſt, 1648; yet we conceive our ſelves obliged to Declare againſt it, and againſt the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning and ſecluding ſo many of the faithfulleſt <hi>Patriots</hi> and <hi>aſſertors</hi> of the publick intereſt of the Kingdom; And alſo againſt the moſt inſolent ſubverſion and alteration of the <hi>constitution</hi> of the <hi>Supreme judicatorie</hi> of the Kingdom, conſiſting of the <hi>Kings Perſonall</hi> or <hi>Virtuall Preſence, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> without whom (as we have been alwayes taught and informed) no Law can be enacted or repealed; The <hi>confirmation</hi> and <hi>inviolable ſettlement</hi> of which happie <hi>Nationall conſtitution,</hi> with its <hi>preſervation,</hi> were the grounds of our <hi>engagements,</hi> and no <hi>change</hi> or <hi>alteration</hi> of the ſame: Whereas, now, to the unexpreſſible grief of our Souls we ſee a moſt ſtrong and feirce <hi>combination</hi> in the <hi>Generall</hi> and <hi>Armies Councell of Warre,</hi> and <hi>others</hi> of their <hi>partie</hi> (ſet forth to the view of us all, in that <hi>Modell</hi> of theirs, called, <hi>The Agreement of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and preſented to that which they call the <hi>Parliament, Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 20th, 1648.) utterly to ſubvert and overthrow the <hi>whole frame</hi> of our foreſaid Legall <hi>Government,</hi> and to introduce and enforce upon us a moſt uncough, ſtrange, and headleſſe confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>tyrannicall Government</hi> of their own deviſing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117236:4"/>and by a new as headleſſe <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of their own <hi>compacting;</hi> and yet all this while, (even whiles they are moſt violently endevouring to overthrow all our National Fundamentall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the very traiterous act for which the Earl of <hi>Straford</hi> and <hi>Cant':</hi> dyed, and which they now lay to the Kings charge to deſtroy him) moſt fallaciouſly and hypocritically they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and ſtrugle to perſwade us (as, in pag: 29th, of their ſaid <hi>Agreement of the People) that they are farre from any deſire or thought to aſſume or exerciſe a Law-giving</hi> (theſe are their own words) <hi>or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall power over the Kingdom, or to meddle in any thing, ſave the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall ſettling of that power in the moſt equall or hopefull way</hi> (as they pretend) <hi>for Common-Right and Safety; And this, they ſay, they humbly tender to us, to conſider, and accept of, if we pleaſe;</hi> Wheras, alas, we know, and <hi>ancient experience</hi> hath taught us to know, <hi>That a Tyrants or Conquerors, Pray, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an irreſiſtible, Command;</hi> And this alſo is it, we thus juſtly complain of and declare againſt.</p>
            <p>But, in the third place, in relation to our <hi>engagement</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> to defend and preſerve our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>freedoms</hi> (in this our, late, moſt famous and honourable <hi>City of London</hi>) according to Law; we are moſt heartily ſorie for the too laſt occaſion that we have to publiſh, and reveal the moſt evident <hi>Perverſion of our Cauſe</hi> under this conſideration alſo. For, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, to enjoy a <hi>Propriety</hi> in our eſtates, with a <hi>freedome</hi> from <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Monopolies, Ship-money,</hi> and other illegall <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Taxes,</hi> the <hi>liberty</hi> of our <hi>perſons</hi> from unlawfull <hi>arreſts</hi> and <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments,</hi> contrary unto <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> our freeborn <hi>Engliſh Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> were raiſed (for their <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>defence</hi>) moſt freely and even prodigally to lay out our perſons and purſes: We are, now, not onely in danger of <hi>intolerable ſlavery</hi> inſtead of <hi>freedome</hi> and <hi>liberty,</hi> according to Law; But, to have our <hi>Franchiſes</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> as <hi>Freemen of this City</hi> voted and rent from us. The deep wounding thoughts whereof do ſo affect and peirce our hearts, that we cannot any longer forbear mournfully to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and Declare, That, ſince the 7th of <hi>December</hi> laſt, we are not onely deprived of our <hi>Freedome</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> to make choice of <hi>ſuch Common Councell-men,</hi> who have all along approved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to God, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> men faithfull in their truſt; they being, now, made uncapable of being choſen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117236:5"/>becauſe of their <hi>honest Activity</hi> for the <hi>Perſonall. Treaty;</hi> And that, by an <hi>Ordinance</hi> made after this ſuppoſed crime was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And, now, as a ſad fruit of it, through many <hi>Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell-men</hi> moſt illegally and forcibly choſen, in part of a <hi>Common-Councell,</hi> is paſſed a <hi>Petition,</hi> which, at beſt, ſhews the <hi>framers</hi> and <hi>promoters</hi> thereof, onely to minde <hi>Earthly things,</hi> not a word of any religious or <hi>heavenly concernment,</hi> being once mentioned in it; And, it is intituled, <hi>The Petition of the Commons of the City of London:</hi> Which is not onely a foule injurie and blemith unto the truly religious and cordiall <hi>Commons</hi> thereof; but fills us alſo with fear of future ſore breaches of our <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> and <hi>City-liberties,</hi> if not to the totall <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the <hi>whole frame</hi> of the <hi>well-conſtituted</hi> and long experienced <hi>good Gouernment</hi> of one of the moſt glorious and renowned <hi>Cities</hi> in the Chriſtian world. All which moſt injurious irregularities we cannot chooſe, as <hi>Citizens,</hi> but with ineffable greif of heart, here, Declare and complain of, being in conſcience obliged hereunto, even by the <hi>Oath of Freemen;</hi> viz: <hi>The Franchiſes and cuſtomes of this City you ſhall maintain.</hi> So that, whereas, we fought for the <hi>defence</hi> of our <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> by Law,<note place="margin">Exact Collect. p. 5.</note> that our <hi>Engliſh Spirits</hi> might not be intimida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or beſlaved by the Kings deſigne of bringing in of <hi>Germane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borſe:</hi> We are, now, ſo farre from ſeeing any <hi>ſure Foundations, for our liberties</hi> and <hi>freedome,</hi> according to Law, that we look upon our ſelves in exceeding great danger (upon that <hi>Common ples</hi> of the <hi>Army, Neceſſity</hi>) to be miſerably ſubjected to <hi>Martiall-Law,</hi> inſtead of being ruled by the <hi>Municipall-Law</hi> of the Kingdom,</p>
            <p>And yet, as if nothing ſhould be wanting to make us <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletely miſerable,</hi> and <hi>exquiſitely to pervert our Cauſe</hi> throughout; When both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> were in an hopefull way not onely of being reconciled, but of ſettling the Kingdome in a way that would have anſwered, (in ſome competent meaſure, for the preſent) the expenſe of our <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>treaſure,</hi> and our <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-engagement</hi> alſo; we are now, not onely diſappointed in our hopes thereof: But, His Majeſties <hi>Royall Perſon</hi> (the <hi>defence</hi> and <hi>preſervation</hi> whereof, though ſo carefully provided for, by the many <hi>Declarations</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the frequent <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in our ſtreets by the beat of the Drum, at the beginning of theſe Wars, by our <hi>Proteſtation May</hi> 5th, 1641, and by our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117236:5"/>
               <hi>Solemn League and Covenant;</hi> yet, as if the end of our engaging with the <hi>Parliament</hi> had been for the <hi>ruine</hi> of the <hi>Kings perſon</hi> and <hi>regall Authority</hi>) His Majeſties <hi>Perſon,</hi> we ſay, is not onely in extreme danger, by being expoſed unto a <hi>Tryall</hi> without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant either from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> or the <hi>Laws of the Land:</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is thereby plunged into ſuch a <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> as is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether derogatorie to and inconſiſtent with the <hi>Kings Honour,</hi> which we profeſſe in our <hi>Covenant,</hi> is the 3d part of our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> for which we engaged. <hi>Artic.</hi> 6. That the <hi>world,</hi> therefore, (to whom we appealed, when we entred into <hi>Covenant</hi> to preſerve and defend the <hi>Kings Majeſties Perſon, and authority,</hi> in the <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of the true <hi>Proteſtant-Religion,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Kingdom) yea the <hi>Lord God himſelf, Angels</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> may bear witneſſe with our Conſciences, that we have no thoughts or intentions (nor ever had) to diminiſh His <hi>Majeſties juſt power and greatneſſe,</hi> and that we the <hi>Subſcribers</hi> hereof are not <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breakers,</hi> but do utterly diſlike and diſavow the preſent proceedings againſt him, either to the taking away of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Crown,</hi> much leſſe his <hi>life,</hi> the very thought whereof we from our ſouls deteſt and abhor; We do, hereby, moſt freely, faithfully and plainly diſcharge our <hi>conſciences,</hi> and do teſtifie our <hi>loyaltie</hi> unto the Kings Majeſtie according to the duty of our allegiance, expreſſed in the foreſaid <hi>Proteſtation, May,</hi> 5th, 1641, and the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi> And we do, hereby, further declare, that when we ſo cordially concurred with the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at firſt, in the <hi>oppoſition</hi> of the Forces raiſed by the King (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by <hi>evill Counſellors</hi>) as we propounded the <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of our <hi>Religion, Parliament, Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties:</hi> ſo, alſo, to preſerve, and not to ruine the <hi>Kings Perſon;</hi> but, mainly <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the wicked from his throne, that ſo it might be eſtabliſhed in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to Him and his royall Poſterity;</hi> But, we ſay, not to pluck Him out of it, and to bring him to an <hi>Arbitrary tryall</hi> for his life, both in reſpect of his <hi>Judges</hi> and their <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſumme, therefore, we have (in all theſe moſt weighty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects) too great and juſt cauſe to be extraordinarie ſenſible, that the bringing of the King (the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Common wealth</hi>) to a <hi>tryall</hi> for his life, before an <hi>arbitrary</hi> and <hi>illegall power,</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by <hi>no Law</hi> of God or Man, and the moſt ſtrange, irregular
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117236:6"/>and unparallel'd <hi>proceedings,</hi> and contemptuous <hi>carriages</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward His Majeſtie, The putting down of the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and, The reſtraining of ſo many <hi>eminent Members of Parliament,</hi> by the <hi>Generall Councell of Officers</hi> in Arms, <hi>againſt all Laws</hi> of God and Man, the known <hi>priviledges of Parliament,</hi> the <hi>liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and their <hi>juſtification</hi> of all theſe <hi>exorbitances,</hi> in print, inſtead of <hi>Repentance</hi> and deep <hi>humiliation</hi> for the ſame, is but a ſad <hi>prologue</hi> to the enſuing <hi>ſlavery</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> of all the <hi>Free-born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of this Realm: For, if the <hi>Head</hi> and moſt eminent <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Common wealth,</hi> legally to be protected from <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>tyranny,</hi> by ſo many <hi>Oaths, Covenants, priviledges, Laws</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements,</hi> be thus <hi>tyrannically</hi> and <hi>barbarouſly,</hi> already, inſulted over, and trampled under feet, like <hi>duſt in the ſtreets,</hi> by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious <hi>Military power;</hi> We, who are inferior to them in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and not invironed with ſo many <hi>priviledges</hi> and <hi>protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> cannot but moſt juſtly fear and expect far greater <hi>inſolencies</hi> and intolerable <hi>preſſures</hi> to be unmercifully exerciſed on us by them, when theſe <hi>pillars</hi> and <hi>foundations</hi> are not onely thus <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> but even quite <hi>removed</hi> and <hi>ſet-by;</hi> According to our Saviours own words. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.25. <hi>If they have called the maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more wil they call them ſo, that are of his houſhold?</hi> In ſad and ſerious conſideration hereof, therfore, we ſay, again and again, we cannot poſſibly keep ſilence, though it be an evill nay, becauſe it is ſo evill a time: But, as, <hi>profeſſors</hi> of the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> which teacheth no ſuch <hi>Doctrines,</hi> as theſe fore-mentioned, and as are, <hi>now adayes</hi> ſo unbluſhingly practiſed, in relation to the <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> and to the reſt of his <hi>free-born Subjects,</hi> without any reſpect, or leaſt diſtinction to their <hi>places</hi> or <hi>qualities;</hi> That we may, as much as in us lyes, wipe off that foul <hi>blot</hi> and ſcandalous <hi>ſtain</hi> that will (otherwiſe) inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably fall upon <hi>Religion,</hi> by this moſt horrid <hi>breach</hi> of our <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> eſpecially in relation to our King; that <hi>profeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel</hi> in other Kingdoms may not alſo ſuffer by being caſt out of <hi>royall protection,</hi> for the ſin of ſome (pretended) <hi>profeſſors</hi> among us; And, that we our ſelves (when the approaching <hi>Earthquake,</hi> which is like to be in the three Kingdoms by fearfull commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and endles wars, &amp; inevitably like to attend the intended <hi>depoſure,</hi> or <hi>violent death</hi> of our <hi>Soveraign King,</hi> ſadly falls upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117236:6"/>us) may not have <hi>outward miſery,</hi> and <hi>inward guilt</hi> to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>without</hi> and <hi>within</hi> us, even our <hi>Conſciences</hi> flying in our faces, for our (at leaſt ſeeming) <hi>conſent</hi> unto it, by our <hi>ſinfull ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> But that we may (in the <hi>ſingleneſſe</hi> and <hi>ſincerity</hi> of our hearts) waſh our hands and clear our <hi>innocencie</hi> in the ſight of God and the whole Chriſtian world: We do not onely, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, make this our juſt <hi>Apologie</hi> that we are far from the <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of the <hi>breach of our Covenant</hi> in any part or branch of it; But, in <hi>particular,</hi> in reference to that of the Kings <hi>Perſon,</hi> ſo clear and innocent, that we do declare our <hi>Deteſtation</hi> and Souls <hi>abhorrency</hi> of that moſt <hi>diſloyall action;</hi> conceiving it to be <hi>ſuch a ſin,</hi> as Men muſt create a <hi>New Name,</hi> for, and God a <hi>New Hell</hi> or <hi>puniſhment</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>And, thus, now, having (in the unfeined <hi>ſincerity</hi> of our hearts) witneſſed a good <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> as in the fight of God, and Men; not from a factious, ſeditious, vain-glorious, or peeviſh <hi>Spirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> or in the leaſt tinctured vile <hi>malignity,</hi> or <hi>apoſtacie</hi> from the <hi>common cauſe of Religion, Liberty</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of the Kingdom; Though we fear not <hi>perſecution</hi> (for righteouſneſſe ſake in being true to our principles) from thoſe who have power, now, in their hands: yet, not knowing whether by Gods <hi>permiſſive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Satan may not caſt ſome of us into priſon</hi> for, thus, ſetting our <hi>Conſciences</hi> at <hi>liberty;</hi> We therefore commit our Souls, in this our <hi>well doing,</hi> unto God, as unto a <hi>faithfull Creator,</hi> hyding our ſelves under the <hi>ſhadow of his wings,</hi> till theſe <hi>calamities</hi> be over paſt, and looking unto Jeſus, who hath aſſured us, <hi>That whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall forſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father or mother, or wife or children, or lands for his Name and Truths ſake, he ſhall receive an hundreth fold, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life.</hi> We have therefore hereunto ſubſcribed our Names with our hearts and hands.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
